"Cancer from Benzene from the Preservative
Sodium Benzoate in Beverages"
Benzene,
a carcinogen that
can cause cancer in humans,
can form in beverages
containing benzoate preservatives
and certain acids
for example, Fanta soda.
Interesting that
Coca Cola chose to disclose
that the artificial colors
it uses can cause ADHD symptoms
rather than
just not using them.
Anyway, the U.S.
Food and Drug Administration
was informed
by the soda industry
about the hazard back in 1990,
yet, 15 years later, was still
finding it in some soft drinks.
This prompted a national survey
of nearly 200 beverages
for the presence of benzene
in soda and other beverages.
The maximum contaminant level
of benzene considered safe
by the U.S Environmental
Protection Agency
is zero, in water supplies,
though that's not always
possible to reach
since benzene
spews from cigarettes,
car exhaust,
and fireplaces.
So, the European Union
allows one part per billion,
and the United States ended up
allowing five parts per billion
since it would be too costly
to push for less cancer.
California holds the line
at one part per billion,
but its goal for public health
is 0.15 parts per billion
based on cancer risk
from leukemia
because a lifetime exposure
to one part per billion
would cause seven additional
people per million to get cancer
who otherwise wouldn't.
Okay, so,
how did the beverages do?
Of the 199 beverages tested,
37 percent had no
detectable benzene,
and another third had less
than one part per billion,
but 40 beverages exceeded the
European and California water standards,
and 18 violated
U.S. federal standards.
However, soda is
not the only source.
In a survey
of 451 beverage samples,
benzene was found
as a heat-induced contaminant
of carrot juice for babies.
And 94 percent of the
carrot juice for infants
had detectable levels
of this carcinogen
with average concentrations
around two parts per billion,
but no benzene was found in
unheated fresh carrot juice.
Obviously, water standards
are much stricter,
but if the only
safe intake is zero,
any avoidable exposure to
benzene should be avoided.
And tainted soft drinks
are definitely avoidable.